It's Sunday night. You just had a nice meal,
إنه مساء يوم الأحد. لقد تناولت وجبة جيدة،
maybe some dessert, and you're on the couch with
وربما بعض التحلية، وتجلس على الأريكة
some popcorn and you want to watch a movie.
ومعك بعض الفشار وتريد مشاهدة فيلم.
How do you pick what to watch?
كيف تختار ما تشاهد؟
Being a data driven person,
بما أنني شخص مهتم بالبيانات،
I love to check the ratings and reviews on Rotten Tomatoes,
أحب تفقد التصنيفات والمراجعات على موقع Rotten Tomatoes،
which is a popular movie rating website.
وهو موقع مشهور لتقييم الأفلام.
This list they have here is so useful.
القائمة التي لديهم هنا مفيدة جدًا.
The Rotten Tomatoes top 100 movies of all time list.
قائمة أفضل 100 فيلم على الإطلاق في موقعRotten Tomatoes.
As written here, movies with 40 or more critic reviews are eligible for this list.
كما هو مكتوب هنا، الأفلام التي حصلت على 40 مراجعة من النقاد فأكثر هي المؤهلة للانضمام لهذه القائمة.
That's critic reviews, so ratings from
هذه مراجعات النقاد، لذا التصنيفات من المشاهدين
regular movie watchers like you and me aren't included in these calculations.
العاديين مثلي ومثلك غير موجودة في هذه الحسابات.
It's sorted by this adjusted score metric which combines
فهي مخزنة بواسطة مقياس نتائج معدل الذي يجمع
the rating and number of critic reviews for each movie to create this adjusted score.
التصنيف وعدد مراجعات النقاد لكل فيلم لإنشاء هذه النتيجة المعدلة.
The idea being that movies with fewer critic ratings have
فكرة أن الأفلام التي حصلت على تصنيفات نقد أقل لها
an easier path to getting that 100% score or close to it.
مسار أسهل في الحصول على نتيجة 100% أو أقرب.
Let's scroll a bit here.
لنقم بالتمرير قليلاً هنا.
Okay, so E.T., I've never actually seen
حسنًا، فيلم E.T، لم أشاهد حقًا
Steven Spielberg's 1982 masterpiece despite hearing lots about it.
الفيلم الرائع إنتاج 1982 من إخراج Steven Spielberg على الرغم من أني سمعت عنه كثيرًا.
It's currently 11th on this list with a 98% rating and 114 critic reviews.
حاليًا هو رقم 11 في هذه القائمة بتصنيف 98% و 114 مراجعة نقاد.
Let's check it out. Okay, so there's that 98% rating.
فلنراجع هذا. حسنًا، هنا تصنيف 98%.
This number is a bit deceiving though.
هذا الرقم خادع.
It's actually the Tomatometer score,
بالرغم من انه المقياس على موقع Rotten Tomatoes،
which is the percentage of
ما النسبة المئوية
approved Tomatometer critics who have given the movie a positive review.
لنقاد موقع Rotten Tomatoes المعتمدين الذين أعطوا الفيلم مراجعة إيجابية.
But okay, there's this audience score here, 72%.
لكن هنا نتيجة المشاهدين 72%.
That metric wasn't included in that top 100 list.
لم تكن هذه النتيجة موجودة في قائمة أضل 100 فيلم.
That's a pretty massive gap.
هذه فجوة كبيرة للغاية.
Maybe this movie isn't that amazing.
ربما لا يكون هذا الفيلم رائعًا.
Also, wouldn't it be cool to compare this critic's score and also the audience score
أيضًا، ألن يكون من الجيد مقارنة نتيجة النقاد هذه ونتائج المشاهدين
for all of these movies to see which movie really truly is the best?
بين كل هذه الأفلام لنرى أي منهم أفضل حقًا؟
Also to find the worst best movie if you will.
وأيضًا لتجد أسوء فيلم بينهم إذا أردت.
I'm picturing a scatterplot with four quadrants,
أنا أتخيل مخطط بياني مبعثر بأربعة أجزاء،
like this one, but with different axis labels and values.
مثل هذا، لكن بأسماء محاور وقيم مختلفة.
We'd have audience score on the horizontal axis and critics score on the vertical one.
سنحصل على نتائج المشاهدين على المحور الأفقي ونتائج النقاد على المحور الرأسي.
That would put amazing movies with
سيضع هذا الأفلام الرائعة التي حصلت على نتائج
high audience and critics scores in the top right quadrant
مشاهدين ونقاد عالية في المربع الأعلى الأيمن
then critically underrated movies in the bottom
ثم الأفلام ذات التصنيف المنخفض بشدة في المربع الأسفل
right quadrant with high audience scores and low critics scores,
الأيمن التي حصلت على نتائج مشاهدين عالية ونتائج نقاد منخفضة،
and critically overrated movies in the top
ثم الأفلام ذات التصنيف العالي في الربع الأعلى الأيسر
left with low audience scores and high critics scores.
التي حصلت على نتائج مشاهدين منخفضة ونتائج نقاد عالية.
Also, I don't trust every single reviewer necessarily.
أيضًا، أنا لا أثق في كل مراجع بالضرورة.
One person I do though,
بالرغم من ذلك أثق في شخص واحد،
the late great Roger Ebert.
العظيم Roger Ebert.
For lots of people,
بالنسبة للكثير من الناس،
Roger Ebert's was the only review they needed because he explained the movie in
كانت Roger Ebert هو المراجعة الوحيدة التي نحتاجها لأن شرح الفيلم
such a way that they would know whether they would
بطريقة تخبرك هل
like it or not, his opinion notwithstanding.
سيعجبك الفيلم أم لا بغض النظر عن رأيه.
Wouldn't it be neat if we had a word cloud for each of the movies in
ألن يكون أنيقًا إذا كان لدينا خدمة سحابية للكلمات لكل فيلم من الأفلام في
that top 100 list with Roger Ebert's review text in that word cloud for each movie?
قائمة أفض 100 فيلم مع نص مراجعة Roger Ebert في هذه الخدمة السحابية لكل فيلم؟
This cool little word cloud generator in Python can help us out.
يمكن أن تساعدنا هذه الخدمة السحابية الصغيرة للكلمات في Python.
Having a word cloud for each movie would give us
الحصول على خدمة سحابية للكلمات لكل فيلم قد يعطينا
a snapshot of what makes each movie great.
لمحة عما يجعل الفيلم عظيمًا.
This word cloud library also has the ability to use stencils,
كما يمكن للخدمة السحابية للكلمات هذه أن تستخدم قوالب الاستنسل،
so we could take the movie poster for each movie and surround it with
يمكننا أن نأخذ الملصق الدعائي لكل فيلم ونضع حوله
a stencil and then put the word cloud around the poster image.
قالب استنسل ثم نضع الخدمة السحابية للكلمات حول ملصق الفيلم.
That'd be really cool. So, to create both of these visualizations,
سيكون هذا رائعًا. لذا، لإنشاء مؤثرات العرض هذه،
the data is in a few different spots and
البيانات في مكانين مختلفين و
it will require some craftiness to gather it all,
سيتطلب الأمر بعض الحرفية لتجميعها كلها،
but you can definitely do it.
لكن يمكنك بالطبع فعلها.
This is actually going to be so awesome.
سيكون هذا رائعًا حقًا.
I'm so excited for you to see the final products.
أنا متشوق جدًا لأجلك لأري المنتج النهائي.